{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Sybil Ludington is nicknamed the “female” counterpart of this figure. William Dawes and this man were given similar tasks by Joseph Warren. This man’s most famous act occurred on “the eighteenth of April, in Seventy-Five” and is the subject of a Henry Wadsworth Longfellow poem that states \"one if by land, and two if by sea.\" For ten points, name this silversmith who warned of approaching British troops during a “midnight ride.”",
      "answer": "Paul Revere"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these structures built by the Axumite Kingdom was taken to Rome but returned to Ethiopia after Italy signed a UN agreement. The earliest known type of this object was comprised of 120 metric tons of red granite, and was meant to commemorate Senusret I in Heliopolis. These structures were said to symbolize the sun god Ra and are topped with a pyramid-shaped capstone. For ten points, name this type of tall, four-sided, monument from Ancient Egypt.",
      "answer": "Obelisks"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this nation, Paul Schäfer [[SHAY-fer]] led an agrarian community known as Dignity Colony that doubled as a post-war refuge for Nazis. The economic policy of a regime in this nation was influenced by the El Ladrillo [[lah-DREE-yoh]] study, first published by the \"Chicago Boys.\" A left-wing leader likely killed himself while defending this nation's Moneda [[moh-NEH-dah]] Palace. Augusto Pinochet [[pee-noh-SHEH]] took power in a 1973 coup in, for ten points, what South American nation?",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Chile",
        "República de Chile"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting of this ruler in his study shows a clock in the background at 4:13 a.m and a law code on a table. Paul Delaroche [[deh-lah-ROHSH]] painted a more realistic version of a painting where the names of Charlemagne and Hannibal can be seen on rocks below this leader. That painting by Jacques-Louis David [JAHK LOO-wee DAH-veed]] shows this ruler crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French Emperor depicted at battles like Austerlitz and Waterloo.",
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I of France 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this ecosystem, deaths attributed to the mountain pine beetle created ladder fuels that resulted in a 1988 wildfire. Drawings and paintings from the Hayden Expedition and the photographs of William Henry Jackson helped make the case for this place's status. The 4900 bison which live here comprise a namesake herd that is the largest in the United States. In March 1872, the first national park status was granted to, for ten points, what Wyoming-centered home of Old Faithful?",
      "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
    },
    {
      "question": "An ancient Indo-European example of these systems from the Vučedol [[VOO-cheh- dol]] culture in Croatia was based on Orion. According to a popular myth, the institution of one of these systems by Chesterfield's Act in 1750 resulted in riots around London. Examples of these systems in Europe are named for Julius Caesar and Pope Gregory XIII [[the thirteenth]]. For ten points, name these systems used to organize time into lunar months.",
      "answer": [
        "Calendar",
        "Vučedol calendar",
        "Julian calendar",
        "Gregorian calendar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's manager, \"Colonel\" Tom Parker, stopped him from playing Tony in the 1961 film adaptation of West Side Story. Ed Sullivan initially declared this man's performances \"unfit for family viewing\" after witnessing his \"gyrations\" during a performance on the Milton Berle Show. In 2019, the city of Memphis funded an expansion of this man's estate, Graceland. The \"King of Rock n' Roll\" was, for ten points, what Tennessee singer of Hound Dog\" and \"Heartbreak Hotel\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Elvis Presley or Elvis Aaron Presley",
        "either underline portion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man used the proceeds from his Lancaster Caramel Company to start his most famous business. This man built a namesake \"Industrial\" boarding school in a company town he established in Pennsylvania in 1903. During World War Two, this man’s factories produced \"Ration D Bars,\" a special type of confectionary designed to resist melting. For ten points, name this American founder of a chocolate bar and confectionary company.",
      "answer": "Milton Snavely Hershey"
    },
    {
      "question": "The only known recording of this man is him repeating the first line of \"La Marseillaise\" in mocking French. The Ems Dispatch was purposefully released to the press by this man to discredit the government of Napoleon III. This minister annexed the province of Alsace-Lorraine following the Franco-Prussian War. The rise of Wilhelm II led to the deposition of, for ten points, which \"Iron Chancellor\" who masterminded the unification of Germany?",
      "answer": "Otto von Bismarck 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was able to flee Nazi Germany after his consultation and analysis of the royal Princess Marie Bonaparte led to a lifelong friendship between the two. The heiress to Tiffany & Co., Dorothy Burlingham, was in a relationship with this man's daughter and fellow psychoanalyst, Anna. This man developed the idea of the id, ego, and superego, which were founding ideas of psychoanalysis. For ten points, name this Austrian psychologist who wrote The Interpretation of Dreams.",
      "answer": "Sigmund Freud or Sigismund Schlomo Freud 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this man's speeches included what is now known as the \"Economic Bill of Rights.\" This man served as assistant secretary of the Navy during the Wilson administration. This president attempted to curb the \"Four Horsemen\" by packing the Supreme Court. The Tennessee Valley Authority and Social Security Administration were part of this president's main domestic program. For ten points, name this four-term president who promoted the New Deal.",
        "answer": [
          "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
          "FDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Constitutional amendment was ratified six years after FDR's death, limiting the office of president to two terms.",
        "answer": "Twenty-Second Amendment"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This geographic point was supposedly first explored by the Greek Eudoxus [[yoo- DOX-us]] around 130 BC. This geographic point was believed to be home to the Flying Dutchman, a pirate ship that haunted sailors, and is located in present-day Table Mountain National Park. The man who named this entity gives his name to a beach located on it. For ten points, name this cape in South Africa discovered by Bartolomeu Dias that was considered a safe haven for early sailors.",
        "answer": [
          "Cape of Good Hope or Kaap die Goeie Hoop",
          "or Kaap de Goede Hoop",
          "or Cabo da Boa Esperança"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man, who was the first European to reach India by sea, is commemorated along with Bartolomeu Dias with crosses on the Cape.",
        "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who spent five years in exile in the Netherlands, argued that \"the end of law is...to preserve and enlarge freedom.\" While serving as a secretary, this man authored the Fundamental Constitutions of Carolina. Thomas Jefferson included many of this man's ideas in the Declaration of Independence, although he edited \"property\" to \"the pursuit of happiness.\" For ten points, name this British \"Father of Liberalism\" who wrote two Treatises on Government.",
        "answer": "John Locke"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Locke determined that people are inherently rational, unlike this predecessor of his, who described life as \"solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short\" in his work Leviathan.",
        "answer": "Thomas Hobbes 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This river contains Margaret Island, formerly a base for the Knights of Saint John. The mouth of this river, which was known as Okeanos Potamos in antiquity, contains Apollo's sacred island of Alba. This river's basin was the site of the Vinča [[VEEN-tsuh]] culture, and was crossed by Darius the Great in order to invade the Scythian [[SKIHTH-yen]] realm. The Dacians were separated from the Roman Empire by, for ten points, what river that now runs through European capitals like Budapest and Vienna?",
        "answer": [
          "Danube River or Donau",
          "Donaj",
          "Duna",
          "Istros"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Danube also runs through this city, formerly known as Pressburg, which is now the capital of Slovakia.",
        "answer": [
          "Bratislava",
          "Pozsony"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To advertise this city at the 1904 World's Fair, Giuseppe Moretti created the tallest cast-iron statue in the world depicting Vulcan wielding a hammer. This city's mining significance gave the local KKK chapter easy access to dynamite, allowing them to terrorize Black citizens in the 16th Street Baptist Church bombing. In a call for direct action against segregation, Martin Luther King, Jr. wrote the treatise \"Letters from [this city's] Jail.\" For ten points, name this industrial Alabama city.",
        "answer": "Birmingham"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This fellow Alabama city was the starting point of a Civil Rights march to Montgomery which crossed the Edmund Pettus Bridge.",
        "answer": [
          "Selma",
          "Selma to Montgomery Marches"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An emperor of this dynasty established the Four Commanderies in Korea, the only successful Chinese occupation of the peninsula. This dynasty's dominance of Vietnam was temporarily undermined by the Trung Sisters' rebellion. This dynasty was briefly interrupted by the Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty of Wang Mang. This dynasty's collapse led to the Three Kingdoms period. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese dynasty that shares its name with the country's majority ethnic group.",
        "answer": "Han Dynasty or Hàncháo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wang Mang, whose brief reign ended in abject chaos, was a scholar of this Ancient Chinese philosopher, whose principles he hoped to impose on Chinese society.",
        "answer": [
          "Confucius",
          "Confucian",
          "Kong Fuzi",
          "or Kongzi",
          "or Master Kong 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A statue of this man was commissioned in the United States for the thousandth anniversary of the Althing. The tale of the lost merchant Bjarni Herjólfsson [[BYAR-nee hare-YOHLF-son]] inspired this man to travel west. This explorer encountered the Skraelings [[SKRAY-lings]], who killed his brother Thorvald in a skirmish outside of L'Anse aux Meadows [[LAHN see MEH-doh]]. The region of Vinland was discovered by, for ten points, which Norse explorer and son of Erik the Red?",
        "answer": [
          "Leif Erikson",
          "Leif the Lucky",
          "or Leifr hinn Heppni"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leif Erikson's father, Erik the Red, is credited with founding the first European settlement on this large semi-arctic island, which in 2009 became autonomous from Denmark.",
        "answer": [
          "Greenland",
          "Kalaallit Nunaat",
          "or Grønland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A governor of this state, who ran in the 2016 presidential primaries using the slogan \"Our American Revival,\" lost a reelection bid to Democratic educator Tony Evers. The protests following the murder of Jacob Blake led to unrest in this state's city of Kenosha, which was followed by the Kyle Rittenhouse incident. Scott Walker once governed, for ten points, what northern state that saw protests in the cities of Madison and Milwaukee?",
        "answer": "Wisconsin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The protests in Kenosha were organized by this antiracist political and social movement which formed following the George Zimmerman acquittal.",
        "answer": "Black Lives Matter or BLM"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Wild West",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Wild, Wild West, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Occupation of horse-riding cattle herders that became synonymous with the Wild West.",
          "answer": [
            "Cowboy or Cowgirl",
            "Cowpuncher",
            "Buckaroo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived courier service of men on horseback who travelled between the states of Missouri and California.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "Outlaw, known by the pseudonym William H. Bonney, who was shot down by Pat Garrett in New Mexico.",
          "answer": [
            "Billy the Kid",
            "Henry McCarty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who hunted bison out West and built a Dakota cattle ranch prior to serving as vice president to William McKinley.",
          "answer": [
            "Theodore Roosevelt Jr",
            "Teddy Roosevelt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State, formerly known as the Indian Territory, which was opened up to white settlement in 1889, causing a land rush.",
          "answer": [
            "Oklahoma",
            "Oklahoma Land Rush"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for Black soldiers who fought in the Plains Wars of the late nineteenth century.",
          "answer": "Buffalo Soldiers"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Thesis\" put forth by Frederick Jackson Turner that the flux experienced by the North American pioneer shaped America's national character.",
          "answer": "Frontier Thesis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe of the Southern Plains which established an \"empire\" from Texas to Kansas that collapsed in the 1870s due to smallpox.",
          "answer": [
            "Comanche",
            "Comancheria",
            "Comanche Empire",
            "or Nʉmʉnʉʉ Sookobitʉ 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Empire of Charlemagne",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Empire of Charlemagne, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Faith Charlemagne followed, to which he violently converted the Saxons.",
          "answer": "Christianity or Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Germanic people group who formed the majority of the nobility.",
          "answer": "Frankish People or Franks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty of Charlemagne, which included his grandfather Charles Martel and his father Pepin the Short.",
          "answer": [
            "Carolingian",
            "Carlovingian",
            "or Karolinger",
            "or Karlings"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty of Charles Martel and Clovis which preceded the rule of Charlemagne.",
          "answer": "Merovingian ] Dynasty or Merovingians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal city of residence known in French as Aix-la-Chapelle [[ay-lah-shah-PEHL]].",
          "answer": "Aachen ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "843 treaty which split the empire between Louis the German, Charles the Bald, and Lothair.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Verdun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inept king and final Carolingian ruler who failed to prevent the Siege of Paris by Viking raiders.",
          "answer": "Charles the Fat or Charles III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scholar and private secretary of Louis the Pious who wrote a biography of Charlemagne.",
          "answer": "Einhard or Eginhard 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Writing Systems",
      "prompt": "Name the ancient writing systems...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Asian language first written in Oracle Bones from the Shang Dynasty.",
          "answer": [
            "Chinese",
            "Zhōngwén",
            "or Hanzi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Writing system used to transcribe the Quran.",
          "answer": "Arabic or Abjad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mesopotamian writing system of wedges etched in clay.",
          "answer": "Cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "Earliest alphabet that was the ancestor of Greek and Latin scripts.",
          "answer": "Phoenician alphabet"
        },
        {
          "question": "Undeciphered script used by the Minoans on Crete.",
          "answer": "Linear A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Script used to record the victories of Pakal the Great.",
          "answer": "Maya Script or Maya Glyphs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Script, also called Harappan, that has been found on pottery all along a namesake river.",
          "answer": [
            "Indus Script",
            "Indus River Valley Script"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country in which the Ge'ez script is used to write several of its native languages.",
          "answer": [
            "Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia or Ityop'iya",
            "Abyssinia 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This U.S. Constitutional amendment was ratified following a vote in Nebraska. Congress passed the Volstead [[VOHL-sted]] Act to (20 pts)",
        "enforce this amendment’s provisions. This amendment resulted from decades of activism by groups like the Anti-Saloon League and Woman's Christian Temperance (10 pts)",
        "Union, though in 1933 it became the only amendment in U.S. history to be repealed. For ten points, name this constitutional amendment that began Prohibition and banned alcohol in the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "Eighteenth Amendment or Amendment XVIII"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Langobards, who once dominated Italy, claimed this deity saw them first thing on the morning of a battle, granting them victory over the Vandals. Roman interaction with the Suebians [[SWEH-byens]] led (20 pts)",
        "to their conflating this god with Mercury. This deity was often associated with hanged men due to having hanged himself from Yggdrasil [[EEG-druh-sil]] to gain knowledge. The word Wednesday (10 pts)",
        "derives from, for ten points, what chief Nordic deity?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Odin",
        "Woden",
        "or Wutan",
        "or Wotan",
        "or Wodanaz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Leather examples of these object are used in a form of theatre performed by the Kannada people to retell stories like the Ramayana. Taiko [[tah-EE-koh]] drummers and tayū chanters are used in a form of theater using these objects named (*) bunraku [[boon-RAH-koo]] native to Japan. A form of art using these figures grew in popularity in the U.S. in the vaudeville circuits of the 1800s. (*) Ventriloquism is an art form using, for ten points, what objects that usually represent people and are manipulated for theatre."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Puppets",
        "Puppet Theatre",
        "Puppettry",
        "Dolls",
        "Bunraku",
        "marionette before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the Pledge of the Tree, this diplomat guaranteed the procession of the first Umrah pilgrimage by negotiating the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah [[hoo-day-BEE- yah]]. A Pagan-Jewish confederation besieged this man's capital during the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Trench, some time after this man began a war with the Quraysh [[KOO-raysh]] tribe following the Battle of Badr. The capture of (10 pts)",
        "Mecca was accomplished by, for ten points, which general and Prophet of the Islamic faith?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Muhammad ibn Abdullah",
        "Mohammed 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In Map of True Places, Zee Finch returns to this city to check in on her ailing father. In a novel set in this city, Matthew Maule lays a curse on the entire (*) Pyncheon family as well as their residence, The House of the Seven Gables. This city's Pickering Wharf appears in the beginning of Nathaniel Hawthorne's Scarlet Letter. Giles Corey is executed in an Arthur Miller (*) play in, for ten points, what Massachusetts city in which a series of 1692 Witch Trials took place?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Salem, Massachusetts",
        "Salem Witch Trials"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This U.S. state's largest city was the site of Fort Christina, the capital of New Sweden, which occupied the lower reaches of its namesake river. This state's only serious engagement during the American Revolution was the Battle of Cooch's Bridge. (20 pts)",
        "This state's \"Blue Hen's Chicks\" regiment fought at the Battle of Brandywine in a namesake county in (10 pts)",
        "Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this state which saw a British occupation of its largest city, Wilmington."
      ],
      "answer": "Delaware"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Among this document’s new protections was that “no freeman is to be taken or imprisoned… save by lawful judgment of his peers or by the law of the land.” This document was signed on neutral territory between the royal fortress at Windsor Castle (20 pts)",
        "and the headquarters of a group of rebellious barons in a water-meadow alongside the River Thames [[TEMS]] called Runnymede. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this document that King John signed in 1215, placing limits on royal power."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Magna Carta Libertatum",
        "Great Charter of Freedoms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Kingdom of Kapisa [[kah-PEE-sah]] once ruled this country, which hosts the now-ruined Greek-inspired Buddhas of Bamiyan [[BAH-mee-yahn]]. Those statues were demolished in this country by a (20 pts)",
        "Deobandi [[deh-oh-BAHN-dee]] fundamentalist regime, which took power following a Soviet withdrawal. Once led by Hamid Karzai [[hah-MEED KAR-zye]], this country is often referred to as the (10 pts)",
        "\"graveyard of empires.\" In 2021, the U.S. pulled its military out of, for ten points, what Pashtun-majority Middle Eastern country controlled by the Taliban?"
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    }
  ]
}